soft engineering radio episode 140 new
speak with Gilad bracha this is software
engineering radio the podcast for
professional developers on the web at se
- radio dotnet as the radio brings you
relevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on software engineering
topics every two weeks thanks to our
audience and the partners listed on our
website for supporting the podcast so
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio we are
sitting here in the gardens at Microsoft
Research we're here at the DSL Def Con
and our guest today is give out Brava
and welcome thank you so please
introduce yourself our audience so they
know who you are okay so I've been doing
object-oriented language work for more
years than it is fashionable to say but
I'm probably best known for the 10 years
I spent at Sun Microsystems where I was
the keeper of the Java language
specification and eventually the Java
Virtual Machine specification and before
that I was involved with a lot of small
talk work we did I was in a startup that
did I think called strong talk which was
a very fast Smalltalk implementation
that eventually evolved into Javas
hotspot virtual machine and and I've
done in academic circles I'm somewhat
known because I also do research and
publish and things like that and the
past two years I've been working on this
new language called new speak which
hopefully we'll get to talk about yeah
well that's the topic of today's show
and I guess new speak sounds to me
almost like small talk I mean the name
is a little bit
I mean speak talk small new yeah yeah
there is something there definitely so
so can you give us a new speaking a
sentence okay so new speak in a sentence
is a language for the cloud I guess
that's that's the best slogan I can come
up with the the law the real goal of
Newspeak is to create a really nice
environment where you can program
for the web without worrying about the
web without dealing with all these
mechanics of of you know different
languages CSS HTML Dom database back in
whatever in general to create a language
for not just to run in a web browser but
language for a networked world a network
of where language where you very easily
can manage clients that have to on the
one hand be connected to the greater
world and on the other hand should be
able to work offline and interact
natively with your system and that's
that's a vision we're working toward it
wasn't a sentence was it but I'll keep
going I can add more and more concise
yeah yeah exactly a run-on sentence yeah
and from another perspective its small
talk with some of its pragmatic
weaknesses made right so modularity
security interoperability all those
things are not strong points in in small
talk environments and we're we're trying
to change that while at the same time
maintaining what's really wonderful
about it the reflectivity and
flexibility that that you get that makes
small talk programmers so fanatical
about the like yeah so so you mentioned
small talk so small talk is clearly an
influence yeah I guess also on the
syntax to some extent uh yes the syntax
is is very small talk like it's not
exactly the same but definitely small
talk is probably still the largest
influence other influences would be self
and beta I don't know how many people
are familiar with baby I've read the
book whatever that means yeah definitely
that's those those are the three major
influences so what are the influences
from each of those languages like the
top two or something okay so I guess
small talk really still dictates the
it's still a class-based language it
still dictates the the overall feel of
the system self the big influence from
self is this idea of what I call message
based programming that is everything's a
message send or if you're if you're not
familiar with those languages and their
terminology don't think asynchronous
messages as in concurrency but more
virtual method calls every name and you
speak is essentially a virtual method
call and that is an idea that comes from
self the other the beta influence is the
idea of nested classes and the fact that
they can be virtual and overridden and
whole class hierarchies can be mixed in
and things like that that is an
evolution from the beta world mm-hmm
if you say it's a system it's the
overall system is like small talk is it
all also also image based the objects in
the IDE kind of instead of text that
certainly is a current situation because
we're implemented on top of squeeks
motto on now this you have to separate
people often have a difficulty
separating a language from its
implementation right so people speak of
interpreted languages which technically
is a meaningless phrase but if most of
the implementations they know are
interpreted they they tend to associate
that yeah so images in particular are a
double-edged sword and we do not expect
to require implementations to do that we
currently are image based in there there
are advantages to that one of small
talks big problems was getting you know
separating applications from the ID
right this is something that we're doing
differently because because we have real
modularity we can essentially very
easily factor out an application and
save it essentially in a file and that
sort of thing right so if you if you
talk about systems or well cloud-based
stuff based stuff and we talked about
influences then if I were a cynic I
would say there might also be like
negative influences languages you
wouldn't want to influence your one I'm
thinking about JavaScript in particular
is it comparable to JavaScript in any
way does it try to solve some some of
the same problems or is that a
meaningless comparison well of course
you can always compare two languages
javascript is a dynamically typed
language effectively you also get this
idea JavaScript was influenced by self
yeah oh and and again you have objects
and they have slots that it's very
flexible and essentially every
you reference in an object is is it's
like a virtual method call right it can
be bound it they do the lookup versus a
prototype so there's a whole bunch of
broad similarities but javascript is is
is a fairly poorly thought-out language
considering its influences were scheming
small talk it's it's rather sad what
came out but it got lucky it is in a
crucial place it's simply fell into the
right place in the universe and it's
very important and we we are relatively
lucky because a lot worse could have
happened in JavaScript is JavaScript is
a wonderful assembly language it's my
viewpoint it's it's my view is that
people should not be programming the web
directly in JavaScript they should in
whatever they want yeah and they should
file it down and the browser the browser
is evolving into the operating system
and as it evolves it becomes more and
more adequate as a target and fast
implementations are coming online and so
forth so I don't I don't like program
directly in JavaScript partly it's the
language partly it's the tooling which
we'll also yeah but I I really don't I
really want don't want to see a world
where people are forced to always
program in the one true language right
for a company that tried to shove that
down the world's throat you don't have
to mention names yes I think that it's
it's a it's a nice one one very good
propagation vector is through web
browsers and and we hope to get to a
point where we compile to JavaScript and
that works well enough but that's still
something that's that's down the line so
of course if we talk about a new
language one question I have to ask is
why a new language couldn't you solve
the same problem with frameworks based
on existing languages what's the problem
well so for some value solve the problem
right it's all turing-complete but you
this the small dog experience is that
this kind of reflectivity in in the
language is very useful and that that
idea has actually propagated in in
slightly warped form through through
scripting languages right they people
who the communities that use that have
realized that the dynamism is really
powerful and there are many features
that originate in small talks that are
in these languages Ruby is actually very
similar to Smalltalk conceptually though
the syntax and implementation are or
another matter yeah and so doing that in
in a really clean and principled way
actually gives you a lot of leverage Oh
in particular modularity is not a solved
problem in programming languages okay we
don't get the same kind of modularity
then when you think of a hardware module
brock's okay pick up and and simply that
that doesn't happen in programming
languages and I think we have made real
progress we've pushed the
state-of-the-art this is this is
actually academic or scientific but now
we've done and so combining these things
gives you gives you real leverage yeah
so so while I was preparing this
interview I I obviously looked at little
bit about material and you have things
like classes modules namespaces mix-ins
all these different things in some shape
or form can you distinguish the roles of
these you already also said that module
just a minute ago modularity isn't a
solved problem I guess that's about
specifying the semantics of black boxes
in some sense so what did you do in that
space okay so so I must say though the
way just introduced it it's very
misleading because you mentioned all we
have all these different things the
point is we don't have no different okay
let me explain yeah essentially we have
classes but because of two fundamental
design decisions we can actually use
classes and in all these roles right and
so a lot of people think that you know
once you have nested classes it makes
sense you can structure things you could
values classes as your packages as fuel
but in practice it in most languages
doesn't seem to work out and people
argue all we really need something
different and so you add a construct a
package or an assembly or something like
that we use classes top level classes as
module definitions because if that works
because we don't have a global namespace
which is fairly unusual there is no
global namespace in the language at all
and so a top-level class is a
self-contained namespace and doesn't
refer to anything external
to it and so can serve as a real as a
real module definition the nice thing
about using a class as a module is you
can have multiple instances so then you
can do things like side-by-side
deployment which people struggle with in
in other frameworks and go to great
lengths but it comes out naturally right
there is a similarity between them and
if you do them right do you actually can
force them into that role so we the
absence of the global namespace means
that classes can conserve as module
definitions and their instances are
modules because there's no global
namespace the only connection and
instance such a module has to the
outside world has to come through
parameters that are passed to it when
it's instantiated and that is a perfect
fit with what's known as the object
capability model right another I would
start to me a little bit like dependency
injection also that you pass into it
whatever it should be able to work with
well in in a sense but of course the
nice thing is we don't need a dependency
injection framework of getting past your
available environment right so so the
the other key idea of except for a
global namespace is this notion that
everything is is late bound everything
is a method call and this eliminates all
kinds of constructs that were the main
motivation for say for dependency
injection right constructors the fact
that you hardwire names of classes into
your code and then you go and and
develop these rather heavyweight
frameworks to try and get around that
this can't happen because every
reference to a class is really a method
call in our system from virtual classes
yes yeah yes so beta was the first
language to introduce virtual classes
that's now we we get those for free
because we can't do otherwise every name
everything is virtual in our language
everything is is this effectively a
virtual method call that can be
overridden somewhere else and as a
result of that we don't need dependency
injection and as a result of that these
modules also act as mix-ins because when
you just you can let me let me back off
a minute nested classes when they refer
to a superclass that superclass name
isn't something fixed right that too is
a method call which means that
your classes really are mix-ins because
a mixin is really a class with an
abstract superclass right and that
doesn't mean that the superclass is
declared to be an abstract class I mean
is it really the superclass is something
that can change it itself you can think
of it as a parameter or something right
yeah and so when you when we compile a
class we don't really know who its
superclass will really end up being
mm-hm
and so we have to compile everything as
a mixin and and so the top level classes
act as mix-ins as well because they're
the super class should be object or
something implicit in the system and so
we've got mix-ins modules classes and I
think you had a fourth thing but I feel
modules I guess but you're right
instances of a module definition so so
we managed the nice thing is we cover a
lot of ground and get a lot of
expressive power from very very simple
rules based on these two ideas no global
namespace and everything is laid bound
huh we just saw talk here about I don't
know what the name was basically about
designed by contract forms for dotnet
language we have something like that
like pre post conditions in your
language we don't at this point and the
nice thing about this sort of language
is it's very easy to accommodate these
kinds of extensions without without
really having to reform the language or
change the more features you have in a
language the more features you end up
having to add to it so you know
essentially these contracts are you know
in my perspective one of the things we
haven't that's in the spec but isn't
implemented yet
is a very general form of metadata yeah
and that metadata could you know is left
to someone to interpret so it could in
fact include post conditions so if we
did an implementation on dotnet I could
you know have the tooling to take such
metadata and compile it into calls to
Manuel's framework that you were
describing we have a very nice framework
and and implement that that way right so
but we do not we haven't done any
specialized syntax or any snow and we
haven't actually done any any any
support for that right right now it's
fairly conventional in that respect
because we were thinking about
modularity I mean modularity requires
that you can specify what some module
does in some sense
so you know when you can use it in how
that's where the contracts come in
that's certainly true that is one thing
that's nice to have and and certainly we
can do that but that is actually easier
to to fit in to do languages then the
fundamentals of modularity right when
you have a piece of hardware the
hardware doesn't specify anything about
what it does there's a there's a
document somewhere saying that it wants
five volts on this plugin
and something else and if you've poked
up 200 volts in my we might burn up but
it is still a module by virtue of the
fact that it doesn't depend yeah on it
only depends on on the things that are
plugged into it it doesn't have implicit
dependencies on its environment sounds
like you're making an analogy between
hardware and dynamic typing which is
something I've never heard before but I
don't see if you you know if you put the
220 volts on the thing you see it
explodes yeah so it's something what's
wrong well the real world of course
isn't statically typed right you do you
do not have proofs for everything
everywhere you go there's that but the
main point is analogy that that's the
kind of modularity that you really want
is the ability to pick up a piece and
take it and connect it and know that it
doesn't drag along things with it yeah
so imports classical classical imports
are a huge problem because an importing
say the modular style of thing is it
doesn't disconnect you from dependencies
it simply makes them explicit yeah you
move it's like your laptop and you move
it and it's connected to power cable
which goes all the way to the power
station and you take the power station
with you because you you specified
exactly what it is you you have not made
it parametric with respect to testing
right and that's what we're trying to
get away from so since we're talking
about typing static or dynamic so
obviously we're dynamically typed so two
out of the three big influences are
dynamically that is awesome it should
have been obvious but beyond that oh I
have a long-standing religious war going
on this thing I've spent a lot of my
time working on with types unlike most
proponents of dynamic languages I I've
spent a lot of work building type
systems okay
static type systems and and I know what
they are yeah and I know what they are
good for they're mainly good for
documentation documentation for both man
and machine
so it's interesting there the idea that
they make your programs more reliable is
a myth and so and they're they also have
the advantage that it is easier to
optimize but that's not essential that's
been proven time again that most of the
hot spot technology that makes java fast
is is was developed for self and small
talk and it doesn't necessarily rely on
the typing some things do because the
typing is there and people tend to use
that right but the real value is there
humans who read this can see you know
can quickly get an idea what this thing
does and machines can can do that so you
can do a better name completion better
refactoring etc etcetera right so with
machines you don't necessarily mean the
compiler but rather the tooling
following it yes okay and so I'm all for
having what I call pluggable or optional
type systems uh-huh and so the
difference is the conventional approach
is the type system is part of the
language if you don't pass the type
checker your program isn't legal it
won't run right compiler will spit it
back in your face and so the idea with
an optional type system is okay you
write these types you can run a type
checker it can tell you what it thinks
and it does not affect your semantics it
doesn't change what the program does and
it certainly doesn't prevent you from
running the program just as if it had no
types at all okay but then question why
would you run a program whose type
checker even if it's optional tells you
your types are wrong because what type
checkers do is they attempt to prove
that you can your program conforms to
the type system all right and the type
system you know guarantees you that if
you conform to it certain kind of bad
things won't happen that doesn't mean
that if you don't conform to it think
bad things will happen right they can't
prove they do not prove that your
program is bad they prove that your
program isn't good according to their
definition of good and their definition
of good is usually - is always too
restrictive inherently because the only
way to really know if it's good is to do
is the runtime semantics but if I try to
add too
a string you will never make sense right
if you add two to a string it may never
make sense
oh you're assuming that you know what ad
means in a language like this of course
you could have overridden things virtual
yeah I'm saying yeah but but let but do
you in depending how you write this
presumably plus on on two makes sense
and so forth and so yes that will that
may never make sense but that isn't
really the problem I mean this is the
kind of toy example that there are
Tisha's give you but that really isn't
the problem the problems are much more
subtle than that and there are lots of
things that do make sense it's sort of
like the the British or anglo-saxon
legal system versus I believe the
Napoleonic one right are you are you
innocent until proven guilty are you
guilty until proven innocent
right we generally don't don't assume
that you know someone should be arrested
because he can't prove that he didn't do
anything right a type system is
essentially Napoleonic law it arrests
you because you can't show that your
victim you're worthy yeah so it
certainly makes sense to to be able to
that that's one issue is the flexibility
the there are other issues which which
really boil down to documentation yeah
there's go Kay so so one of the amusing
arguments that people bring up often
nowadays what they've learned to
appreciate I DS something that comes
from the small talk world essentially in
the early Lisp world and so forth and
now they tell you ah but the more I DS
can do such a wonderful job refactoring
and without type four information you
probably can't do as well and they sort
of neglect the idea that where did
refactoring come from it came from small
talk and the Java world they didn't
invent this because one of the things
these type systems do is it makes it
hard to invent things it makes it hard
to do meta programming it makes it hard
to do things that the language designer
didn't anticipate as typical use cases
right because then you're type checker
says no I can't prove that that's okay
and and you it's very hard to be
creative the wonderful thing about about
dynamic typing is it lets you express
anything
that that it is computable and and type
systems don't type systems are typically
decidable and they restrict you to a
subset the common the type of people who
favorite static type system say ah yes
but it's fine this is good enough all
the interesting programs you want to
write our will work as type then that's
not that's ridiculous that's the once
you have a type system you don't even
know it interesting programs are there
sure yeah it's a usual problem yeah that
the language you use con restricts the
way you think yes our influences to
everything yeah so let me try to explain
to you what pluggable I have understood
what pluggable type systems are and you
tell me if that's right okay so let me
make an analogy you say it basically
that in a language like Java which has a
static type system there is certain
information you put into the program as
a form of metadata with basically a
special syntax which is types and then
you have a compiler that does some
checks on that metadata but there might
be other interesting metadata for
example the stuff there or well no let
me say there are other interesting
checks that for example today static
analysis tool can perform for which
there is no specially treated metadata
with special syntax but you might use
for example Java annotations to put into
the program additional metadata that
then specialized static analysis tools
used and what you're saying is a
language should basically have no you
know singled out preferred type system
or metadata system but rather you should
be able to add different kinds of
metadata that then are evaluated or
checked by different kinds of tools
depending on what you want to do exactly
also you you've got it now to elaborate
upon one point in order for this to work
it's very important that none of the
type systems change what your program
does right because once once the typical
case we have because then they'll
interact and then you can't keep adding
new ones and so you can't you know check
for race conditions or information fleex
or you know whatever whatever flavor of
the month you want or non-null or their
there's all kinds of analyses and once
you say ah but once I can show that that
that it is supposed to be now I'll put
in a cast or a check then your program
doesn't
have the same and it'll interact with
another system and it just won't scale
it's like it's like metadata is like has
no side effects and presence yes exactly
so and that's also why you said before
that in Newspeak you have a general
metadata system that's for exactly that
reason
yes well have is a strong term or one
that we we have a spec for it okay or
something and we we will get there so
yes that that is the exactly the
motivation well one of the motivations
is viewing types of metadata they're
actually more now our type system for
Newspeak is a non-trivial exercise right
now actually we we allow you again a
legacy of the work I did on strong talk
is we actually allow you to annotate
your code with types we just don't do
anything with them and in fact we I
can't say that we know precisely what
these types will mean because type
checking new speak is harder than type
checking small talk which is what we did
in the strong dog system ok all right so
so then is there I mean another like
tendency today and in compilers with
static type systems like Scala is to use
type inference to make you know to still
have static types with the you know
theoretical or claim benefits but you
don't have to write all the type or type
information all the time and use type
inference sort of compiler can calculate
the types does that play into this stuff
here oh it certainly plays into this
stuff so one of the one of the problems
with type inference is that once you
mandate a certain degree of type
inference in your language it constrains
your type system as well because they're
the types have to be such that you can
plausibly infer them and so there
there's an exact analogy just as a type
system
you know reduces them the set of
programs you can write to to some subset
that that you can actually check once
you decide on language level rules for
type inference it constrains what kind
of type system you can have because it
has to be to fit within that inference
team and so mandatory type inference is
also a bad idea my preference would be
to say okay for the type checker the
types have to be explicit whatever the
type system is
but again it's a tooling issue okay I
would like to have a method browser
where I said oh please infer the types
and it'll fill them in and if it if it
fails then you know that's too bad but
it hasn't it doesn't prevent me from
writing those types it doesn't constrain
how my type system was designed and I in
fact I can use different heuristics
different schemes to to actually do the
inference in some sense a type inference
is just one of possibly many
calculations a tool does with metadata
yes and and that again removes a set of
constraints by not coupling these things
as tightly and interestingly enough the
research the the scheme community has
done matthias for lisen and his students
have done a lot of work on on what they
called soft typing and Corky Cartwright
basically people in the scheme community
and I think after a good many years and
theses they came to the conclusion that
the one of the weaknesses of soft typing
was the emphasis on type inference
because it constrained things so so the
the it's a surface illusion that you say
I don't I don't want to it's nay the
problem isn't with with writing these
annotations or reading them within
within limits the problem is with what
you can express it's often useful to
read these annotations and how whether
they're clutter or readable or what is a
tooling matter yeah oh you present it so
and one last question what is metadata
stuff is it like comparable to Java
annotations in the sense that you have
some generic generalized syntax where
you put these things or didn't you get
to the center so in text big yet since
you're still at specification phase well
so they it is comparable but it is not
the same I mean certainly the idea of
annotations definitely fits with this
but in my view to really make this work
well you should be able to have for a
given set of annotations you should be
able to actually define the syntax and
define essentially a tool that will know
how to interpret the metadata so it'll
be something that says however begin
metadata
essentially look like a comment comments
are also a form of metadata right
treating them formally also is great for
refactoring because then you know where
they belong
and in that comment at some point you
say oh this is metadata of some kind
which will Q which kind of interpreter
you how you want to interpret the rest
and then you can use nice syntax for it
and and also hopefully tool support yeah
code completion I think because that's
one thing I won't I'm not willing to get
rid of I'm yeah that's definitely yeah
so so it isn't supposed to force you to
write it in some little constrained
notation so we're here basically for the
DSL def con is there any support for DSL
and you speak hashes new speak
yeah news because the infuse new speak
and strong talk right yeah you alright
new speak well support the new speak is
a great language for doing the s l's
support is it's not like there's some
feature that was put in press a to do
this but small talk originally was was
fairly good at for domain-specific
languages because the key word notation
is actually very general very readable
people aren't used to reading it as a
general-purpose programming language but
it actually if you look at at notations
people use to define metadata you know
it's it's fairly fairly similar if you
look at things like languages that are
purpose designed for describing gooeys
like zamel and java it's where it's very
similar in a way when you look at those
examples so we use that in our in our
GUI system we we writes new speak code
that looks a lot like you know rows and
columns of gooey things right and it
works well in that sense it works better
than small talk because we allow the
receiver of a method call at the target
of a method invocation if you to be
implicit in in in a lot of cases which
small talk doesn't so that again reduces
clutter and the fact that it's
dynamically typed means that yeah well
you have more flexibility there you
could know about program yeah yes the
meta programming features in general the
fact that you can trap methods messages
that aren't understood and give them
some meaning that so this works very
very well the fact that you can use
syntactically operators in a very
natural form defined methods whose names
are operator names so all that oops
all that really works and and well the
reason I'm speaking at these Alcon is
I'll be giving several example
yeah when I'm looking forward to seeing
that so a couple of last things one is
that just came to my mind I did an
interview well since we were here about
a year ago with Under Hasbrouck and we
talked about c-sharp obviously and about
his thoughts about languages in general
and one thing we talked about was the
idea that language extension is always
also IDE extension so it's also like
what intentional is doing right or MPs
JetBrains
so have you if you're thinking about
being able to define pluggable type
systems optional type systems then would
you foresee a way how these custom
definable type systems can also
influence the behavior of the IDE so you
can for example do code completion based
on some of that metadata sure so so
anders is very right that if you're
serious about your language then then
every every feature in it should have ID
support and so if you extend it it means
you have to assign your ID now in our
case of a pluggable type system or a new
type system isn't strictly a language
extension but it is its new metadata and
and the tools definitely to make this
work you want tools to to support that
now because it's it's very easy to do
meta programming and certainly the local
the core the core reflective libraries
should let you get at that metadata then
you you would have be able to expand
your tooling because our preferred
preferred ID is the one written in
Newspeak right that's the point that now
it's very easy to extend it and modify
it on the fly since you basically you do
ide meta programming it yes yes yes and
so that would be one example of that so
getting back to where we started about
this language being optimized for cloud
computing and the web there is one thing
I came across which is object or
services yes what's that okay so that
that was the original motivation for the
whole thing
the idea here is that typically in in
client applications I started with this
when I started using Gmail now I guess
five years ago
and I was very enthused when I said Oh
finally Google is doing mail finally I
have a mailer I like because I've never
found a mailer I really was satisfied
with yeah and I used it for half an hour
and decided no I don't have a mailer I
like and and and more than that I
realized well that it hit me then rather
belatedly perhaps that what the real
problem was that I wanted something that
behaved like a true native local rich
application in traditional sense and yet
had this coupling to the network and had
the advantages of being coupled to the
network for example the nice thing about
a web app is that no one asks you what
version it is no one no one tells you
I'm using version 2.0 and I'll never
give it up and you have to support it
till the end of time and so forth right
nobody the the question doesn't even
enter people's minds well because you as
the provider of the web app have to make
sure that everything is compatible with
the data if you deal with rich rich
client programs nobody would ask either
that that's true to some extent though
say UI features might change and so but
yeah but yeah the nice so so definitely
you have to make sure that it works with
the data and the traditionally because
you're keeping the data on your server
that you you manage the data yeah now on
the other hand that means that this
thing doesn't really work that well say
if I don't have a good network
connection yep and if I if I need to go
somewhere and it doesn't have that that
immediacy and interactivity sometimes
depending on on unless you have a really
good high bandwidth connection it's
really hard to do so the idea was that
you would write applications that could
run disconnected on your machine and
keep essentially a cache of the data
right on your machine but at the same
time you do want that data to always be
up-to-date and always in the format for
the latest application and so forth and
it's a little when I start to think that
this is similar to what you do with with
things like calendars and things where
you synchronize but right so you
synchronize your data between several
places and given how my mind is warped
around the small bug way of thinking
it's all basically a persistent set of
objects
mm-hmm and if you could synchronize a
general set of objects this way
essentially the heap representation of
your persistent data right then you
would have these objects both on on a
server providing a service and that's
where objects as a service comes from ah
right and you and you could sync or
download it to machine your machine
essentially by synchronization make sure
that the local changes you've made when
you are offline
you know take hold there is a design
pattern I think called half object half
protocol or something which basically
says that you design replicated objects
in a way that they basically feel like
if they were local on both sides of the
replication channel and then the
replication basically happens
automatically in case of the pattern yet
the program it you of course and what
you're saying basically is that you have
language support for that essentially
well we aim to have language support and
we have we have basic features in the
language that are there are we don't
even have the specification for it we
have we have ideas and we have basic
features which we believe make it a lot
easier to do this because this is a hard
problem yes and to do that one of the
idea is that because everything's laid
bound right that simplifies matters
there's a code doesn't depend on
representation yes and and things like
that that's that's very useful it means
that if you need to change or update
things you you are always going through
some intermediary that'll let you do
that so that's that's the in a nutshell
the idea of objects is software services
and and you could actually build
services this way so you would deliver
say a word processor as an application
you you'd run it nice and locally and it
would you'd have your documents as
objects that you would have locally and
if you're landing in Kamchatka somewhere
you can still write your your documents
and you don't have to worry oh there's
no web connection and my Google Docs
aren't available yeah at the same time
whenever I if I needed to collaboration
I could have it in a shared space that
other protocol reach over the network
when I change it would sync up and so
forth so it's a kind of a way to get the
best of both worlds and having a
language which is really good at meta
programming in which objects are only
handled through late bindings so you
have this level of indirection
all these things are things that
basically are key to how we expect that
infrastructure to work and we've done
some experiments but it's it's too early
to really say that we support anything
so what is the state of Newspeak today
what can you or should people use it for
work what can they get it from
well they can get it at Newspeak program
what is the name of the webpage Newspeak
language okay and you know Google will
find it there turns out there are
actually apparently two or three
languages called Newspeak and a tool
called Newspeak which is slightly
annoying but what can you do and but
they but you if Google will find it
though since it since its web 2.0 which
you could have left away a couple of
vowels and you know the name you speak
is is was was carefully thought and and
occasionally you hit someone who's
offended by it because of our well and
so forth some people get it and most a
lot of people get it and occasionally
you find someone who gets it and it's
all upset but this is mainly a good way
of testing whether people have a sense
of humor or not so the idea actually is
not a scheme to to oppress the world but
rather the thing about new speaking in
normals novel was that every edition of
the Newspeak dictionary was smaller
because they were cutting down on the
vocabulary with the idea of limiting how
people could express themselves but
basically the idea that you would be
able to cut the vocabulary that is you
could actually take things out of
software minimize the language little
bit like in the Lisp tradition small
language with powerful features that let
you do everything well we're certainly
in that tradition but the thing I
learned that Java was and I'm sure
Anders would agree right any any widely
used languages that you or any widely
used software the curse of these things
is the curse of compatibility nothing
can ever be taken out yeah yes and the
nice thing about this vision which is a
fairly futuristic vision of when you get
to the point where your data is backed
up on a server is that the world is
connected now and you should be able to
find who's using what and you can you
get just as you reform their data to me
to fit the latest version of the program
you know if they have
if they're using an idiom that you know
you've decided is no good and can be
rewritten or something you put out a
script that that'll rewrite it and you
know where to find all these programs so
this is a bit extreme and that's sort of
the blue sky research side of this but
the idea was yes wouldn't it be
wonderful if I could take things out if
we could minimize
a shrinkable language rather than a
global one yeah I got better okay so so
it's at this time it's basically in a
development stage there isn't probably
much that normal people should use it
for it's definitely for the early
adopter right so people who get enthused
about languages and playing and stuff
certainly can do it cuz because we built
you know product quality stuff with it
at kailyn's okay but you had you still
have there's a few things you still have
to know what you're doing one of the
great problems in the small talk world
has been deployment because again this
issue of the ID and basically you deploy
the ID with your application and not
everyone wants to do that because of the
modularity we can separate things out of
the ID and we're we're gonna get there
fairly soon but right now it isn't quite
a push-button process to say okay now
packaged my application you still have
to know a bit more than that to get
something that's that's like to get a
dot XE out of right but we're we're on
that track so that's mainly the thing
that would limit people now because
other than that I certainly on Windows
you can do professional-looking stuff
okay so right now I I don't want to
foist it on anyone who's who wants a
turnkey solution but people who are
interested in these issues who are
enthusiasts and early adopters can
certainly you can build stuff with it I
think that that'll run and yeah so I
guess people who decided that Scala is
now mainstream enough so that it's
boring they can now go to new speak it's
it's fresh enough so that it has its
edges it's yes I think that's definitely
I wouldn't call Scala boring but yeah
but yes that certainly is sounds like a
fair characterization of how radical you
should be okay and again we're we've
been at this for about two years
been more or less eight years or more
and it takes time to evolve to the that
point sadly and I hope we will get there
faster than that but before everybody
has internet everywhere and
synchronization and offline working
isn't necessary anymore
I'm not worried about that yeah I agree
okay anything else you want to say
before we wrap this up just thank you
for taking the time and you know you
certainly seem to at least have
communicated this to one person because
you seem to have gotten it and hopefully
that way your papers are good enough so
we're reading for 15 minutes I can ask
these questions so I hope I hope people
you have a broad audience and my website
is overrun by people floating Newsweek
listen thank you thank you thanks for
listening to software engineering radio
software engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SA radio team
by our website or you can advertise for
sa radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team at se - radio
net or if it is specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of se radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crow and the pot safe music network for
the music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle